<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Investigating Summer Bridge Programs Designed to Accelerate Mathematics Preparation for STEM Degrees</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299943.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299943</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Richardson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With support from the NSF Improving Undergraduate STEM Education Program: Education and Human Resources (IUSE: EHR), this project aims to serve the national interest by studying the effectiveness of summer bridge programs at improving academic achievement and persistence of STEM students.  The project will focus on improving the mathematics preparation of incoming students before they enter their first year of college. The project will compare the impact of a two-week residential summer bridge program to a nonresidential, online version of the program. Students in both bridge programs will be able to strengthen mathematics skills by using an adaptive online testing program called ALEKS PPL (Assessment and Learning in Knowledge Spaces Placement, Preparation, and Learning). The project anticipates that the bridge programs will improve student success in mathematics courses.  As a result, it has the potential to to diversify STEM majors at the University by increasing the number of students who declare a STEM major and improving first to second-year retention of students enrolled in STEM programs. Results from the research will inform activities at the University, but also have the potential to improve STEM recruitment and retention activities across the country, particularly in states that are moving away from developmental mathematics coursework to remediate deficiencies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will contribute to quantitative research about STEM summer bridge programs by using empirical data to test the impact of a residential bridge program compared to a nonresidential version using a randomized controlled study design (30 students assigned to each for two years for a total of 120 students in the study). Research questions will be answered by analyzing  the performance of STEM students in the two programs, considering the average difference in ALEKS scores, time spent in ALEKS modules,year one and year two retention rates, and improvement of initial mathematics placement. The project builds upon previous effective bridge programs described in the literature, as well as recent successful projects at Northern Kentucky University focused on improving recruitment and retention of STEM students. Students in both bridge programs will use ALEKS PPL, an approach that has resulted in improvements in mathematics placement by one course for students who spend ~30 hours working on the ALEKS learning modules. Students participating in the residential program will also be exposed to STEM-related research experiences that highlight the importance of mathematical content knowledge. All students will be supported throughout their first year through a seminar series that has demonstrated success in STEM programs at Northern Kentucky University. The seminar series will help students: assume responsibility for their own learning both in and out of the classroom; acquire academic, personal, and social skills essential to success in college and beyond; develop effective communication skills; establish a supportive cohort with fellow students; and create a four-year plan that leads to graduation. In addition, these seminars also assist students in exploring STEM career options and career-preparation activities.  The NSF IUSE: EHR Program supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students.  Through the Engaged Student Learning track, the program supports the creation, exploration, and implementation of promising practices and tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/17/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1900036</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Russell</LastName>
<EmailAddress>russellk@nku.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/17/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharmanthie</FirstName>
<LastName>Fernando</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Fernando@nku.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/03/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Walters</LastName>
<EmailAddress>walterske@nku.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/03/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/17/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maureen</FirstName>
<LastName>Doyle</LastName>
<EmailAddress>doylem3@nku.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/03/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bethany</FirstName>
<LastName>Bowling</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bowlingb2@nku.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/03/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brooke</FirstName>
<LastName>Buckley</LastName>
<EmailAddress>buckleyb1@nku.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/03/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northern Kentucky University</Name>
<CityName>Highland Heights</CityName>
<ZipCode>410990001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8595725768</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Nunn Drive, UC 405</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
